Hashing. Today we're going to do some amazing stuff with hashing.
我们今天将研究关于哈希的一些神奇的内容
And, really, this is such neat stuff, it's amazing.
对 真的是相当精巧  非常神奇
We're going to start by addressing a fundamental weakness of hashing.
我们由一个哈希的根本缺陷谈起
And that is that for any choice of hash function
对于任意哈希函数而言
There exists a bad set of keys that all hash to the same slot.
都存在一个不好的键集  所有键都会哈希映射到同一个槽
OK. So you pick a hash function.
当选择一个哈希函数时
We looked at some that seem to work well in practice,
我们会找一些在实际应用中很不错的
that are easy to put into your code.
而且还很方便地嵌入到你的代码中的
But whichever one you pick, there's always some bad set of keys.
但不管你选择哪个 总有一些不好的键集
So you can imagine, just to drive this point home a little bit.
你可以想像  这只是为了让我们更接近问题的本质
Imagine that you're building a compiler for a customer
试想你为一个客户建立了一个编译器
and you have a symbol table in your compiler
有一个专门为编译器准备的符号表
and one of the things that the customer
客户的要求之一是
is demanding is that compilations go fast.
比较快速的编译过程
They don't want to sit around waiting for compilations.
他们可不想编译的时候就坐在旁边苦等
And you have a competitor who's also building a compiler
你的一个竞争对手也建了一个编译器
and they're going to test the compiler,
当客户准备测试编译器时
both of your compilers and sort of have a run-off.
假设两个编译器都有 一些类似溢出之类的问题
And one of the things in the test
在测试过程中
that they're going to allow you to do is
客户会要求你
not only will the customer run his own benchmarks,
不仅能运行客户的一套测试基准
but he'll let you make up benchmarks
还要为对方的编译器
for the other program, for your competitor.
建立一套测试基准
And your competitor gets to make up benchmarks for you.
而你的竞争对手也会为你建立一套测试基准
So and not only that, but you're actually sharing code.
不仅如此 你们还要共享代码
So you get to look at what the competitor is actually doing
你要知道对方在做什么
and what hash function they're actually using.
他们采用的是什么哈希函数
So it's pretty clear that in this circumstance,
这很显然 在这种情况下
you have an adversary who is going to look at
你的竞争对手就会查看
whatever hash function you have and figure out OK,
你用的是什么哈希函数
what's a set of variable names and so forth
然后对症下药 给你找一个
that are going to all hash to the same slot
全部都哈希到同一个槽的键集
so that essentially you're just chasing through a linked list
这样一来 当你的哈希表查找数据时
whenever it comes to looking something up.
就相当于是在遍历一个链表
Slowing down your program enormously compared to
这样很大程度上减缓了程序的运行速度
if in fact they got distributed nicely
比起均匀分布的哈希表
across the hash table which is,
它运行要慢得多
what after all, you have a hash table
因为毕竟  那才称得上
in there to do in the first place.
用到了哈希表
And so the question is, how do you defeat this adversary?
但问题是  如何战胜你的对手？
And the answer is one word.
答案只要一个词
One word. How do you achieve?
一个词 如何做到？
How do you defeat any adversary in this class?
如何打败这个班里的所有对手？
Randomness. OK. Randomness. OK.
随机性 对 就是随机性
You make it so that he can't guess.
你有了随机性那对手就没办法了
And the idea is that you choose a hash function at random.
解决方案是随机选择一个哈希函数
Independent. So he can look at the code,
相对独立地 对手可以查看代码
but when it actually runs,
但当程序运行时
it's going to use a random hash function that
它将使用一个随机的哈希函数
he has no way of predicting what the hash function
他没办法预测  你最终将用到的
is that will actually be used.
是哪个哈希函数
OK. So that's the game and that way he can provide an input,
这样的话  即使对手能提供一组输入
but he can't provide an input
但他们却不能
that's guaranteed to force you to run slowly.
保证它能减缓你的程序的运行速度
You might get unlucky in your choice of hash function,
你可能会随机到一个比较差的哈希函数
but it's not going to be because of the adversary.
但实际上不会 因为对手没办法预测
So the idea is to choose a hash function
所以问题关键是  选择哈希函数时
at random,
要随机选择
independently from the keys that you're,
与输入的哈希运算的键
that are going to be fed to it.
保持相对独立
So even if your adversary can see your code,
这样即使你的对手能看到你的代码
he can't tell which hash function
他也不能确定  实际运行时
is going to be actually used at run time.
会用到哪一个哈希函数
Doesn't get to see the output of the random numbers.
他无法预测随机数的输出
And so it turns out you can make this scheme work
看上去这个方法切实可行
and the name of the scheme is universal hashing,
这个方法的名字叫全域哈希
OK, is one way of making this scheme work.
一个能实现该方案的哈希方法
So let's do some math. So let U be a universe of keys.
那么 我们写些数学定义  设U为键的全域
And let H be a finite collection -- -- of hash functions
H是哈希函数的有限集
mapping U to what are going to be
H的哈希函数将U的键映射到
the slots in our hash table.
哈希表的槽里
OK. So we just have H as some finite collection.
好的  我们有一个有限集H
We say that H is universal
我们称H是全域的
——if for all pairs of the keys, distinct keys
——如果满足 对于所有的键对
——so the keys are distinct, the following is true.
——键与键两两互异 那下面的推论就能成立
So if the set of keys, if for any pair of keys I pick,
在这个函数集H里  对于任意键对
the number of hash functions that hash
都会将它们哈希映射到同个位置的
those two keys to the same place
哈希函数的数目
is a one over m fraction of the total set of keys.
等于|H|/m
So let me just, so to view that,
也可以这样看
another way of viewing that is if H is chosen randomly
从另一个角度看 如果哈希函数h是
——from the set of keys H,
随机地从函数集H里选出
the probability of collision between x and y is what?
那x和y发生碰撞的几率是多少？
What's the probability if the fraction of hash functions,
如果我们选出了的一部分哈希函数...
OK, if the number of hash functions is H over m,
又或者说 选出的哈希函数的数目是H/m
what's the probability of a collision between x and y?
那么 x和y碰撞的几率是多少？
If I pick a hash function at random.
如果我随机选择一个哈希函数
So I pick a hash function at random,
那我就随机选一个哈希函数
what's the odds they collide?
它们碰撞的几率是多少？
One over m.
1/m
Now let's draw a picture for that,
让我们画张图
help people see that that's in fact the case.
来帮助理解  实际上是这样子的
So imagine this is our set of all hash functions.
假设这是所有哈希函数组成的集合
OK. And then if I pick a particular x and y,
如果选择一对特定的x和y
let's say that this is the set of hash functions
假设这个子集里的哈希函数
such that H of x is equal to H of y.
能使得h(x)=h(y)
And so what we're saying is that the cardinality of that set is
那么这个子集的势
one over m times the cardinality of H.
等于1/m * |H|
So if I throw a dart and pick one hash function at random,
就像投掷飞镖  随机投到一个哈希函数
the odds are one in m that the hash function
哈希函数落在这个特殊子集里的
falls into this particular set.
几率是1/m
And of course, this has to be true
当然 对于每对x和y
of every x and y that I can pick.
上述等式都是成立的
Of course, it will be a different set,
另一边  则是不同的函数子集
a different x and y will somehow
它们会把不同的x和y
map the hash functions differently,
映射到不一样的地方
but the odds that for any x and y that I pick,
但对于所选的任意x和y
the odds that if I have a random hash function,
通过随机选择的哈希函数
it hashes it to the same place, is one over m.
哈希到同一个位置的概率是 1/m
Now this is a little bit hard sometimes
这里有一点理解上的困难
for people to get their head around
有时让人脑袋转不过来
because we're used to thinking of
因为习惯性会想
perhaps picking keys at random or something.
随机地选择键之类的
OK, that's not what's going on here.
跟这里的情况不一样
We're picking hash functions at random.
我们是随机地选择哈希函数
So our probability space is defined over the hash functions,
所以我们的概率空间 是给哈希函数定义的
not over the keys.
而不是键
And this has to be true now for any particular two keys
对于所选的任意两个不同的键
that I pick that are distinct.
这个等式都是成立的
That the places that they hash,
如果它们用的是
this set of hash functions,
这个子集里的哈希函数
I mean this is like a marvelous property if you think about it.
如果你仔细思考一下 就会发现这是一个不可思议的特性
OK, that you can actually find ones where
因为这意味着
no matter what two elements I pick,
对于任意的两个键值
the odds are exactly one in m that
一个随机抽取的哈希函数
a random hash function from this set
将它们哈希到同个位置的概率
is going to hash them to the same place.
正好是1/m
So very neat.
非常精巧
Very, very neat property
非常 非常美妙的特性
and we'll see the mathematics associated with this is very cool.
我们将会看到 它相关的数学运算真的非常酷
So our theorem is that if we choose h randomly
那么 我们的定理是 如果从哈希函数集H里
from the set of hash functions H,
随机地选择函数h
and then we suppose we're hashing n keys into m slots in Table T
然后假设我们要将n个键 放进T表的m个槽里
——then for given key x
对于给定的键x
——the expected number of collisions with x
它发生碰撞的期望次数
——is less than n over m.
小于n/m
And who remembers what we call n over m?
有谁还记得n/m是什么吗？
Alpha, which is the, what's the term that we use there?
α 我们用什么术语来称呼它？
Load factor. The load factor of the table.
装载因子 哈希表的装载因子
OK, load factor alpha.
装载因子α
So the average number of keys per slot
平均到每个槽的键数
is the load factor of the table.
就是哈希表的装载因子
So we're saying, so what is this theorem saying?
那这个定理在表达什么？
It's saying that in fact,
是这样的
if we have one of these universal sets of hash functions,
如果我们有这样一个哈希函数的全域集
then things perform exactly the way we want them to.
那它的运行结果就会跟所预期的一样
Things get distributed evenly.
键的分布很均匀
The number of things that are
对于任意的键
going to collide with any particular key
它发生碰撞的次数
that I pick is going to be n over m.
会等于n/m
So that's a really good property to have.
这真是一个不错的性质
Now I haven't shown you, the construction of U is going,
我还没有解释集合U怎么构建
sorry, of the set of hash functions H,
抱歉 应该是哈希函数集H怎么构建
that that construction will take us a little bit of effort.
我们会在构建这块下一些功夫
But first I want to show you why this is such a great property.
但首先我想解释下 为什么这是一个极好的性质
Basically it's this theorem.
这定理基本上就是这样子
So let's prove this theorem.
那我们来一起证明它
So any questions about what the statement of the theorem is?
对这个定理的表述还有什么问题吗？
So we're going to go actually kind of fast today.
那接下来 我们要讲得快点了
We've got a lot of good stuff today.
因为有很多东西要讲
So I want to make sure people are onboard as we go through.
我想保证大家在整过程中都能跟上
So if there are any questions, make sure, you know,
如果有任何问题  确保你要弄懂
statement of theorem of whatever, best to get them out early
像定理的表述之类的 最好能先理解透彻
so that you're not confused later on
这样在后面
when the going gets a little more exciting. OK?
当内容稍微复杂起来时  才不会感到困惑
OK, good. So to prove this,
好的 开始证明
let's let C sub x be the random variable
设C_x为一个随机变量
denoting the total number of collisions
它表示 哈希表T里的键与x
——of keys in T with x.
发生碰撞的总次数
So this is a total number and one of the techniques
这是一个总数 在随机化算法的
that you use a lot in probabilistic analysis
概率分析里面
of randomized algorithms is
这是经常用到的一种技巧之一
recognizing that C of x is
你会意识到
in fact a sum of indicator random variables.
C_x实际上是指标随机变量的总和
If you can decompose things into indicator random variables,
如果你能将事件分解成指标随机变量
the analysis goes much more easily than
那分析起来就会比
if you're left with aggregate variables.
集中起来的变量容易很多
So here we're going to let
在这里我们把
our indicator random variable be little c of xy,
指标随机变量 设为小写c_xy
which is going to be one if h of x equals h of y and 0 otherwise.
如果h(x)＝h(y) 值为1； 否则为0
And so we can note two things.
可以注意到两点
First, what is the expectation of C of xy.
首先 c_xy的期望值是多少
OK, if I have a process
如果有一个进程
which is picking a hash function at random,
在随机选择哈希函数
what's the expectation of C of xy?
那c_xy的期望值是多少？
One over m.
1/m
Because that's basically this definition here.
因为这基本上就是这里的定义
Now in other words I pick a hash function at random,
换句话说 随机选择一个哈希函数
what's the odds that the hash is the same?
哈希结果相同的概率是多少？
It's one over m.
1/m
And then the other thing is,
另外一方面
and the reason we pick this thing is that
选择这公式的原因是
I can express capital C sub x,
因为我们可以将大写C_x——
the random variable denoting the total number of collisions
这个表示碰撞总数的随机变量
as being just the sum over all the keys
表示为  当y取T中的非x元素时
in the table except x of C of xy.
对应的c_xy值的和
So for each one that would cause me a collision, with x,
那么 对于每个与x发生碰撞的的键
I add one and if it wouldn't cause me a collision, I add 0.
我都给C_x上加1 如果没有发生碰撞 则加0
And that adds up all of the collisions
那这就把表中所有和x发生的碰撞
that I would have in the table with x.
全部都加到一起
Is there any questions so far?
到这里有什么问题没有？
Because this is the set-up.
这部份是理论的基础架构
The set-up in most of these things,
是主要内容的基础架构
the set-up is where most students make mistakes
是大多数学生容易出错的地方
and most practicing researchers
很多研究员新手
make mistakes as well, let me tell you.
也同样在这里出错
And then once you get the set-up right,
但只要你把架构做好了
then working out the math is fine,
之后的数学工作就好做了
but it's often that set-up of how do you
而通常 这些架构是将...
actually translate the situation into the math.
实际情况转换为数学问题的建模结果
That's the hard part. Once you get that right,
这部分是难点 只要你搞明白了
well, then, algebra, we can all do algebra.
那接下来的代数运算...
Of course, we can also all make mistakes doing algebra,
当然 代数运算中也可能出错
but at least those mistakes are much more easy to check
但至少检查起来容易得多
than the one that does the translation.
相对于转换过程而言
So I want to make sure people are sort of understanding of
所以我想保证大家都能理解
how that's set up.
这个是如何架构的
So now we just have to use our math skills.
现在就要用到我们的数学技能了
So the expectation then of the number of collisions is
碰撞次数的期望值是
the expectation of C sub x
C_x的期望值
and that's just the expectation of just plugging the sum of y
等于这个期望值...这里是对所有c_xy的求和
and T minus the element x of c_xy.
y属于T 而且y不等于x
So that's just definition.
这就是定义
And that's equal to the sum of y
也就等于对所有E[c_xy]求和
and T minus x of expectation of c_xy.
y属于T 而且y不等于x
So why is that?
为什么会等于这个
Yeah, that's linearity.
对 期望的线性性质
Linearity of expectation, doesn't require independence.
这是期望的线性性质 和独立性无关
It's true of all random variables.
对任意随机变量都是成立的
And that's equal to, and now the math gets easier.
还等于 下面的数学比较简单
So what is that?
这是多少？
One over m.
1/m
That makes the summation easy to evaluate.
这样一来 总和就很容易算了
That's just n minus one over m.
得出(n-1)/m
So fairly simple analysis and shows you why we would love
相当简洁的分析 这就是为什么..
to have one of these sets of universal hash functions
我们会喜欢上全域哈希的原因
because if you have them,
因为一旦有了它
then they behave exactly the way you would want it to behave.
那结果就会像我们期望中的那样
And you defeat your adversary
这样一来你就能打败你的对手了
by just picking up the hash function at random.
只需随机地选择一个哈希函数
There's nothing he can do. Or she.
他或她 都会对此无能为力
OK, any questions about that proof?
对这个证明还有什么问题没有？
OK, now we get into the fun math.
好的 现在进入有趣的数学部分
Constructing one of these babies. OK.
造这些可爱的孩纸
This is not the only construction.
这并不是唯一的构造方法
This is a construction of a classic universal hash function.
只是一种构造经典的全域哈希的方法
And there are other constructions in the literature
一些出版物里会有其它的结构
and I think there's one on the practice quiz.
在练习测试中会用到其中一个
So let's see. So this one works when m is prime.
咱们看这里 这个是当m为质数时成立
So it works when the set of slots is a prime number.
即当槽的总数 为质数时有效
Number of slots is a prime number.
槽数为质数
So the idea here is we're going to decompose
做法是 把全域里的任意键k
any key k in our universe into r plus 1 digits.
分解成r+1位
So k, we're going to look at as being a k 0, k one, k_r
可以把k看成k_0 k_1 ...k_r
where 0 is less than or equal to k sub I,
这里  k_i大于等于0
is less than or equal to m minus one.
小于等于m-1
So the idea is in some sense we're looking at
这种做法的思想是
what the representation would be of k base m.
把k用"m进制"来表示是什么样子
So if it were base two, it would be just one bit at a time.
如果我们用二进制  那每一位就最多有1
These would just be the bits.
这些就是不同的位
I'm not going to do base two.
我们不打算用二进制
We're going to do base m in general
我们把它一般化成"m进制"
and so each of these represents one of the digits.
这里每一个都代表一个位
And the way I've done it is I've done low order digit first.
我们这里把第一个数定为最低位
It actually doesn't matter.
实际上没有关系
We're not actually going to care really about what the order is,
实际上并不用太在乎顺序
but basically we're just looking at busting it
我们实际上是要换一种k的表示方式
into a twofold represented by each of those digits.
把它打散成一位一位的数字
So one algorithm for computing this out of k is
把k换算成"m进制"的一种算法是
take the remainder mod m.
不断地对k除m再取余
That's the low order one.
第一次先用k对m取余 求出最低位
OK, take what's left.
然后将k除m的商
Take the remainder of that mod m.
再用来对m取余
Take whatever's left, etc.
然后再把商在除m  一直循环下去
So you're familiar with the conversion to a base representation.
大家应该对改变进制的运算很熟悉了
That's exactly how we're getting this representation.
我们就是用它 来求出这种表达式的
So we treat, this is just a question of taking the data
这只是一个表示方法的问题
that we've got and treating it as an r plus one base m number.
而我们这里是将k  看成一个r+1位的m进制数
And now we invoke our randomized strategy.
现在就可以引入随机化策略了
The randomized strategy is going to be able to
随机化策略就是
have a class of hash functions
我们哈希函数集合的选取
that's dependent essentially on random numbers.
是取决于随机数的
And the random numbers we're going to pick is
而我们要用到的随机数则是..
we're going to pick an a at random
我们要随机地选择一个数a
——which we're also going to look at as a base m number.
——同样地  我们也把a看成是m进制数
For each a_i is chosen randomly
a的每个位a_i都是在0到m-1这个区间里
——from 0 to m minus one.
随机选择的
So one of our, it's a random if you will,
它是随机的...如果你愿意
it's a random base m digit.
它是随机的m进制数
Random base m digit.
随机的m进制数
So each one of these is picked at random.
这里每一位都是随机选择的
And for each one we, possible value of A,
对于a的每一位 可能的值
we're going to get a different hash function.
我们都找一个对应的 不同的哈希函数
So we're going to index our hash functions by this random number.
所以我们是用这一个随机数来表示哈希函数
So this is where the randomness is going to come in.
这就是产生随机性的地方
Everybody with me?
大家跟得上吗？
And here's the hash function.
接下来是哈希函数
So what we do is we dot product this vector
那我们要做的就是  拿这个向量(a)
with this vector and take the result, mod m.
跟这个向量(k)点乘  乘积再对m取余
So each digit of k of our key
那么 键k的每一位
gets multiplied by a random other digit.
都会乘以一个随机数
We add all those up and we take that mod m.
我们把乘积全部加起来 再对m取余
So that's a dot product operator.
注意这里是点乘
And this is what we're going to show is universal,
我们要证明 这种哈希是全域的
that this set of h sub a, where I look over that whole set.
集合h_a是在整个哈希函数集中的一个全域集
So one of the things we need to know is
我们要先了解的事情之一是
how big is the set of hash functions here.
这里的哈希函数集有多大
So how big is this set of hash functions?
这个哈希函数集究竟有多大?
How many different hash functions do I have in this set?
在这个集合里有多少种不同的哈希函数？
It's basic 6.042 material.
这是6.042课程的基本问题
It's basically how many vectors of length r plus one
这就是相当于计算  对于一个长度为r+1的向量
where each element of the vector is a number of 0 to m minus one,
向量的每个元素 都是从0到m-1之间取值
has m different values.
也就是可能有m个不同的值
So how many? m minus one to the r.
那总共有多少种可能的值？ (m-1)^r
No. Close. It's up there.
不对 但很接近了
It's a big number. m to the r plus one.
这是一个大数  m^(r+1)
Good. It's m, so the size of H is equal to m to the r plus one.
没错  H的大小等于m^(r+1)
So we're going to want to remember that.
我们要记住这个结论
OK, so let's just understand why that is.
先来理解一下为什么是这样
I have m choices for the first value of A. m for the second, etc.
a的第一个元素有m个选择 第二个也是 以此类推
m for the r th.
第r个元素也有m个选择
And since there are plus one things here, for each choice here,
因为这里有r+1个元素 对于每一个
I have this many same number of choices here, so it's a product.
我们都有这么多种的选择  所以是乘积
OK, so this is the product rule in counting.
这是计数的乘法法则
So if you haven't reviewed your 6.042 notes for counting,
如果你们忘了6.042课程里的计数方面的内容
this is going to be a good idea to go back and review that
最好回去复习一下
because we're doing stuff of that nature.
因为我们是根据那个规则来运算的
This is just the product rule.
这里用到的是乘法定则
Good. So then the theorem we want to prove
好的 我们想要证明的定理是
is that H is universal.
H是全域的
And this is going to involve a little bit of number theory,
这个会涉及到一些数论问题
so it gets kind of interesting.
还是挺带感的
And it's a non-trivial proof,
而且这将是一个犀利的证明
so this is where if there's any questions as I'm going along,
如果讲解过程中有任何问题
please ask because the argument is
请主动提问  因为这个论证
not as simple as other arguments we've seen so far.
会比我们目前学习到的其它论证都要难
OK, not the ones we've seen so far have been simple,
不像我们之前看过的论证那么简单
but this is definitely a more involved mathematical argument.
但这个问题 绝对会涉及到更多数学论证
So here's a proof. So let's let, so we have two keys.
好 我们来证明  假设我们有两个键
What are we trying to show if it's universal,
我们要证明H是全域的
that if I pick any two keys, the number of hash functions
那H就满足  把任意两个键
for which they hash to the same thing
哈希到同一位置的 哈希函数的数量
is the size of set of hash functions divided by m.
等于集合H的大小除以m
OK, so I'm going to look at two keys.
好的 我们来研究下这两个键
So let's pick two keys arbitrarily.
首先任意选择两个键
So x, and we'll decompose it
把x分解成
into our base r representation and y, y_0, y_1 --
r进制的表示形式 同样 y也分解成y_0, y_1...y_r
So these are two distinct keys.
这是两个互异的键
So if these are two distinct keys,
如果这是两个互异的键
so they're different,
那么它们就不相同
then this base representation has the property
那么 在这种数位表达式  它就表现为
that they've got to differ somewhere.
它们在某个位是不同的
Right? OK, they differ in at least one digit.
至少有一个位是不同的
OK, and this is where most people get lost
这是大多数人都忽略的
because I'm going to make a simplification.
我们来将它简化一下
They could differ in any one of these digits.
它们可能在任意数位有不同
I'm going to say they differ in position 0
假设它们的0位不同
because it doesn't matter which one I do,
哪个位不同并没有关系
the math is the same, but it'll make it
数学原理都是一样的
so that if I pick some said they differ in some position i,
但如果我选择它们在第i位不同
I would have to be taking summations as you'll see
那接下来要做加法的话
over the elements that are not i, and that's complicated.
就要把i排除出来 问题会变得很复杂
If I do it in position 0,
但如果选择0位
then I can just sum for the rest of them.
那我只需把剩下的位相加就好
So the math is going to be identical
不管在哪一个位置相异
if I were to do it for any position
数学运算都是相同的
because it's symmetric.
因为它是对称的
All the digits are symmetric.
所有的位都是对称的
So let's say they differ in position 0,
所以这里假设它们在0位不同
but the same argument is going to be true
但即使它们在其他位置互异
if they differed in some other position.
结论还是成立的
So let's say, so we're saying without loss of generality.
这样的假设保证大部分情况都适用
So that's without loss of generality.
不会丢失其一般性
Position 0.
第0位
Because all the positions are symmetric here.
因为这里所有的位都是对称的
And so, now we need to ask the question for how many
现在我要问
——hash functions in our universal,
——全域集里据称有多少哈希函数...
purportedly universal set do x and y collide?
会使得x和y发生碰撞？
OK, we've got to count them up.
我们要把数目数出来
So how often do they collide?
它们碰撞的频率是多少？
This is where we're going to
这里将引出
pull out some heavy duty number theory.
一些重量级的数论
So we must have, if they collide
如果发生碰撞
——that h sub a of x is equal to h sub a of y.
——那么h_a(x)=h_a(y)
That's what it means for them to collide.
这就是发生碰撞
So that implies that the sum of i equal 0 to r of a sub i x sub i
亦即∑(i=0到r)a_i * x_i
is equal to the sum of i equals 0 to r of a sub i y sub i mod m.
等于∑(i=0到r)a_i * y_i
Actually this is congruent mod m.
实际上这里是全等  两边还要对m取余
So congruence for those people
这个全等号 对于那些
who haven't seen much number theory,
没怎么接触过数论的人来说
is basically the way of essentially,
可以理解为
rather than having to say mod everywhere in here
我们不需要对左边的每一项都取余
and mod everywhere in here,
右边也不需要
we just at the end say OK, do a mod at the end.
这里只需要在最后取余一次就好了
Everything is being done mod, module m.
在最后 等所有都运算完 再取余
And then typically we use a congruence sign.
然后在这里特别地写上一个全等号
OK, there's a more mathematical definition
其实还有一些更数学化的定义
but this will work for us engineers.
但对于我们工程师而言 这已经足够了
OK, so everybody with me so far?
到目前为止 大家都跟得上吧？
This is just applying the definition.
这只是运用了一下定义
So that implies that the sum of i
我们可以推导出
equals 0 to r of a i x i minus y i
Σ(i=0到r)a_i*(x_i-y_i)
is congruent to zeros mod m.
全等于0 对m取余
OK, just threw it on the other side
其实只是移了下项
and applied the distributive law.
然后应用了分配律
Now what I'm going to do is pull out the 0-th position
现在要做的是引出第0位
because that's the one that I care about.
因为这是我所关注的位置
And this is where it saves me on the math,
这就是我之前在数学上做的一个保留
compared to if I didn't say that it was 0.
即使我们假设的互异位不是第0位
I'd have to pull out x_i.
如果引出的是x_i
It wouldn't matter,
也没有关系的
but it just would make the math a little bit cruftier OK,
只是会让数学显得不是很规整
so now we've just pulled out one term.
现在只需抽出一项
That implies that a_0 x_0 minus y_0
推导出a_0*(x_0－y_0)
is congruent to minus ---- mod m.
全等于负的这一大块 对m取余
Now remember that when I have a minus number mod m,
还记得 当用一个负数对m取余时
I just map it into whatever,
我是将它映射到...
into that range from 0 to m minus one.
0到m-1的区间里
So for example, minus five mod seven is two.
举个例子 -5对7取余 等于2
So if any of these things are negative,
所以对于任意负数的取余
we simply translate them into by adding multiples of m
我们只要简单地 转化成加上m的倍数
because adding multiples of m doesn't affect the congruence.
因为加上m的倍数并不影响全等
OK. And now for the next step,
好的 我们的下一步工作
we need to use a number theory fact.
要应用到一个数论事实
So let's pull out our number theory
那我们先把频道转到数论上
textbook and take a little digression
说一点题外话
So this comes from the theory of finite fields.
这源于一个有限域的理论
So for people who are knowledgeable,
对于那些学识丰富的人
that's where you're plugging your knowledge in.
这是你们晒知识的时候了
If you're not knowledgeable,
但如果你不是很博学
this is a great area of math to learn about.
这是一个很值得学习的数学领域
So here's the fact. So let m be prime.
令m为一个质数
Then for any z, little z element of z sub m,
对于任意的z 小写z 属于Z_m中的元素
and z sub m is the integers mod m.
Zm是对m取余后的整数
So this is essentially numbers from 0 to m minus one
实际上 所有整数都是 由0到m-1间的数
with all the operations, times, minus, plus, etc.,
经过加 减 乘等运算变换得来的
defined on that such that if you end up outside
如果这个数的取值范围
of the range of 0 to m minus one,
在0到m-1之外
you re-normalize by subtracting or adding multiples of m
你可以通过加或减m的倍数来使之重新标准化
to get back within the range from 0 to m minus one.
回到0到m-1这个区间里
So it's the standard thing of just doing things module m.
这是一种标准化方法 只需要对m取余
So for any z such that z is not congruent to 0,
对于任意的不全等于0的z
there exists a unique z inverse in z sub m,
存在唯一一个属于Zm的z的倒数
such that if I multiply z times the inverse,
如果用z乘以z的倒数
it produces something congruent to one mod m.
得到的结果对m取余得1
So for any number it says,
对于任意的一个数
I can find another number that
我总能找到另外一个数
when multiplied by it gives me one.
与之相乘得到1
So let's just do an example for m equals seven.
举一个例子 让m等于7
So here we have, we'll make a little table.
我们在这里画一个小表格
So z is not equal to 0,
z不等于0
so I just write down the other numbers.
所以我只需要写出剩余的数
And let's figure out what z inverse is.
我们来算一下z的倒数
So what's the inverse of one?
1的倒数是多少
What number when multiplied by one gives me one?
什么数乘以1会得到1？
One. Good. How about two?
1 好的 2的话呢
What number when I multiply it by two gives me one?
什么数乘以2会得到1？
Four. Because two times four is eight
4 因为2乘以4等于8
and eight is congruent to one mod seven.
8对7取余后全等于1
So I've re-normalized it. What about three?
我们把它标准化了 那3呢？
Five. Good. Five. Three times five is 15.
5 非常好 3乘以5等于15
That's congruent to one mod seven
15对7取余后全等于1
because 15 divided by seven is two remainder of one.
因为15除以7等于2 余1
So that's the key thing. What about four? Two.
就是这样 4呢 2
Five? Three. And six. Yeah. Six.
5呢 3  还有6 倒数是6
Yeah, six it turns out. OK, six times six is 36.
6乘以6等于36
OK, mod seven.
再对7取余
Basically subtract off the 35, gives me one.
减去35 余下1
So people have observed some interesting facts that
人们观察到一些有趣的事实
if one number's an inverse of another,
如果一个数是另一个数的倒数
then that other is an inverse of the one.
那另一个数同时也是这个数的倒数
So that's actually one of these things that you prove
这实际上是你研究群论或场论等理论时
when you do group theory and field theory and so forth.
会证明的事实之一
There are all sorts of
这些全是这类数学中
other great properties of this kind of math.
的某些重要的性质
But the main thing is,
但主要的是
and this turns out not to be true if m is not a prime.
如果m不是质数 这个性质就并不成立
So can somebody think of, imagine we're doing something mod 10.
谁能想一个...假设我们对10取余
Can somebody think of a number
谁能够找出一个
that doesn't have an inverse mod 10?
对10取余后没有倒数的数？
Yeah. Two. Another one is five.
对了 2  还有5
OK, it turns out the divisors in fact actually,
实际上 如果除数...
more generally, something that is not relatively prime,
通俗一点说 如果两个数不是互质的话...
meaning that it has no common factors,
——互质就是指没有公因数
the GCD is not one between that number and the modulus.
那这个数和模数m的GCD(最大公约数)就不是1
OK, those numbers do not have an inverse mod m.
那么 这些数对m取余就求不出倒数来了
OK, but if it's prime,
但如果m是个质数
every number is relatively prime to the modulus.
那么每个数就都会和m互质
And that's the property that we're taking advantage of.
这就是我们要利用到的性质
So this is our fact and so, in this case
那在这种情况下
what I'm after is I want to divide by x_0 minus y_0.
我想要 拿m来除(x_0-y_0)
That's what I want to do at this point.
这就是现在我想做的
But I can't do that if x_0, first of all, if m isn't prime,
不过首先  如果m不是质数
I can't necessarily do that.
那就不必要这么做了
I might be able to, but I can't necessarily.
虽然也可以这样做 但没必要
But if m is prime, I can definitely divide by x_0 minus y_0.
但如果m是质数 我就肯定可以拿它来除(x_0-y_0)
I can find that inverse.
并能够求出倒数
And the other thing I have to do
另一个必须做的事是
is make sure x_0 minus y_0 is not 0.
保证(x_0-y_0)不为0
OK, it would be 0 if these two were equal,
如果x_0等于y_0  这就等于0了
but our supposition was they weren't equal.
但我们假设是它们并不相等
And once again, just bringing it back
再说一次 回到之前的内容
to the without loss of generality,
为了不失一般性
if it were some other position that we were off,
如果我们考虑的不是第0位 而是其他位
I would be doing exactly the same thing with that position.
我也会对它做同样的操作
So now we're going to be able to divide.
现在可以进行除法了
So we continue with our
继续我们的...
——continue with our proof.
——继续我们的证明
So since x_0 is not equal to y_0,
因为x_0不等于y_0
there exists an inverse for x_0 minus y_0.
所以存在（x_0-y_0）的倒数
And that implies, just continue on from over there,
这就能推出...承接着那边的内容
that a_0 is congruent therefore to minus the sum of i
a_0全等于...
equal one to r of a_i, x_i minus y_i times x_0 minus y_0 inverse.
-Σ（i=1)a_i(x_i-y_i)乘以(x_0-y_0)^-1
So let's just go back to the beginning
让我们回到证明的开始阶段
of our proof and see what we've derived.
看看我们推导出了什么
If we're saying we have two distinct keys,
假设我们有两个互异的键
and we've picked all of these a_i randomly,
然后我们随机选出了这些a_i
and we're saying that
并且假设
these two distinct keys hash to the same place.
这两个互异的键被哈希到同个位置上
If they hash to the same place,
如果它们被哈希到同一个地方
it says that a_0 essentially had to
那我们就能推出 a_0实际上是...
have a particular value as a function of the other a_i.
由其他所有的a_i所决定的
Because in other words,
因为换句话说
once I've picked each of these a_i from one to r,
一旦其他a_i都选定下来了
if I did them in that order, for example,
打个比方 如果是按a_1到a_r顺序的话
then I don't have a choice for
那么能发生碰撞的
how I pick a_0 to make it collide.
就只有一个特定的a_0
Exactly one value allows it to collide,
只有一个特定的值会发生碰撞
namely the value of a_0 given by this.
就是由这条式算出的这个a_0
If I picked a different value of a_0,
如果a_0选另一个值
they wouldn't collide.
则不会发生碰撞
So let me write that down.
让我写到黑板上
Thus, while you think about it
同时你可以思考一下
So for any choice of these a_i,
对于任意一组的a_i
there's exactly one of the impossible choices
只有一个 a_0的可能选项
of a_0 that cause a collision.
使之发生碰撞
And for all the other choices
对于a_0的其它所有选值
I might make of a_0, there's no collision.
都不会有碰撞
So essentially I don't have, if they're going to collide,
所以...  如果发生碰撞的话
I've reduced essentially the number of degrees
随机哈希函数的自由组合数
of freedom of my randomness by a factor of m.
就减少了m倍
So if I count up the number of h_a's
如果合计出 让x和y发生碰撞的
that cause x and y to collide,
哈希函数h_a的数量
that's equal to, well, there's m choices,
它就等于...这有m个选择
just using the product rule again.
再次用到乘法定则
There's m choices for a_1 times m choices
对a_1来说有m个选择  乘以a_2的m个选择
for a_2, up to m choices for a_r
直到a_r都有m个选择
and then only one choice for a_0.
但a_0只有一个选择
So this is choices for a_1, a_2, a_r
这些是a_1 a_2... a_r的选择
and only one choice for a_0 if they're going to collide.
如果发生碰撞 a_0就只有一个选择
If they're not going to collide, I've got more choices for a_0.
如果没有发生碰撞  a_0会有更多的选择
But if I want them to collide,
但我想要它们碰撞
there's only one value I can pick, namely this value.
所以只有一个值能选 就是这个值
That's the only value for which I will pick.
这是唯一我能选的值
And that's equal to m to the r,
这里等于m^r
which is just the size of H divided by m.
也就是H的大小除以m
And that completes the proof.
证明完成了
So there are other universal constructions,
当然还有其它的全域架构
but this is a particularly elegant one.
但这是特别精妙的一个
So the point is that I have m plus one,
关键是  我们有m+1个...
sorry, r plus one degrees of freedom
不对 是r+1的自由度
where each degree of freedom I have m choices.
每个自由度都有m个选值
But if I want them to collide, once I've picked any of the,
但如果我想让它们发生碰撞
once I've picked r of those possible choices,
一旦确定了其他r个选择
the last one is forced if I want it to collide.
要发生碰撞的话 最后一个也就已经确定了
So therefore, the set of functions
这样一来 能发生碰撞的函数
for which it collides is only one in m.
就只能是m种函数中的一个
A very slick construction.
非常巧妙的架构
Very slick. OK. Everybody with me here?
非常巧妙 大家都清楚了？
Didn't lose too many people?
有多少人听到崩溃了？
Yeah, question.
[教授]什么问题？
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
学生：...
Well, part of it is, actually this is
嗯 差不多 实际上
a quite common type of thing to be doing actually.
这其实都是一个很常见的运算
If you take a class,
如果你去上一门课
so we have follow on classes in cryptography and so forth,
就例如 像密码学之类的课程
and this kind of thing of taking dot products,
像这些点乘运算
modulo m and also Galois fields
取余运算  还有"伽罗瓦域"
which are particularly simple finite fields
也就是一种比较简单的有限域
and things like that, people play with these all the time.
像这些运算 人们都一直都在做
So Galois fields are like using x order here,
伽罗瓦域是用的是x阶（即有x个元素）
same sort of thing as this except base two.
就跟这里差不多  除了二阶的情况更特殊一点
And so there's a lot of study of this sort of thing.
在这方面有很多的研究
So people understand these kind of properties.
所以人们知道有这些性质
But yeah, it's like what's the algorithm
但世上有没有一种算法
for having a brilliant insight into algorithms?
能让你洞悉一切的算法呢？
It's like OK. Wish I knew.
我也想知道
Then I'd just turn the crank.
那样的话 我就成算法帝了
[LAUGHTER]
[笑]
But if it were that easy,
但如果有那么容易
I wouldn't be standing up here today.
那我今天就不会站在这里了
[LAUGHTER]
[笑]
Good. OK, so now I want to take on
接下来 进入下一个主题
another topic which is also I find,
这个主题也...
I think this is astounding.
相当地犀利
It's just beautiful, beautiful mathematics
非常美丽的数学
and a big impact on your ability to build good hash functions.
对于锻炼你构造好的哈希函数能力 会有很大的帮助
Now I want to talk about another one topic,
那我们现在要讲的另一个主题
which is related, which is the topic of perfect hashing.
跟之前也是相关的 那就是完全哈希
So everything we've done so far
目前为止 我们所做的..
does expected time performance.
都是跟预期时间相关
Hashing is good in the expected sense.
哈希在预期时间上还是不错的
A perfect hashing addresses the following questions.
而完全哈希则是考虑以下的问题
Suppose that I gave you a set of keys,
假设我给你一个键集
and I said just build me a static table
要求你帮我创建一个静态表
so I can look up whether the key is in the table
那我如果要在查看一个键是否在表中
with worst case time.
在最坏的情况下
Good worst case time.
怎样做得更好
So I have a fixed set of keys.
如果有一个固定的键集
They might be something like for example,
举个例子  假设是表里存的是
the hundred most common
最常见的一百个
or thousand most common words in English.
或最常见的一千个的英语单词
And when I get a word I want to check quickly in this table,
当我拿到一个单词 我想要迅速地查一下表
is the word that I've got one of
看看这个单词
the most common words in English.
是不是英语里最常见的单词之一
I would like to do that not with expected performance,
我要的并不是用预期的性能
but guaranteed worst case performance.
但我要确保最坏情况的性能
Is there a way of building it so that I can find this quickly?
有没有相应的建表方法  能让我快速地查找？
So the problem is given n keys
问题是 给定n个键
-- -- construct a static hash table.
——创建一个静态哈希表
In other words, no insertion and deletion.
换句话说 没有插入或删除
We're just going to put the elements in there.
表里一直都是那些元素
of size ---- m equal Order n.
表的大小是m=O(n)
So I don't want it to be a huge table.
我不需要一张很大的表
I want it to be a table that is the size of my keys.
我只想让表的大小刚好和键数一致
Table of size m equals Order n,
表的大小是m=O(n)
such that search takes O(1) time in the worst case.
使得在最坏情况下 查找的时间是O(1)
So there's no place in the table where I'm going to have,
所以在这个表里就不会有多余的空间
I know in the average case,
在平均情况下
that's not hard to do.
这个并不难完成
But in the worst case,
但在最坏情况下
I want to make sure that there's no particular spot
我想确保不会出现...
where the number of keys piles up to be a large number.
一个槽里面堆了大量的键的情况
OK, in no spot should that happen.
我不希望出现这种情况
Every single search I do should take Order one time.
每个查找都应该是O(1)的时间
There shouldn't be any statistical variation in terms of
在查找所需花费的时间上
how long it takes me to get something.
不应有任何变化
Does everybody understand what the puzzle is?
大家都明白这个问题没有？
So this is a great,
这点很重要
because this actually ends up having a lot of uses.
因为它有很大的用途
You know, you want to build a table for something
因为当你要创建一个表
and you know what the values are that
而你已经知道
you're going look up in it.
你要查找的是什么值的时候
But you don't want to spend a lot of space on it and so forth.
你就不希望浪费大量空间等等
So the idea here is actually going to be
那解决方案就是
to use a two-level scheme.
使用一个双级结构
So the idea is we're going to use a two-level scheme
关键是使用一个双级结构
with universal hashing at both levels.
并且在每一级都使用全域哈希
So the idea is we're going to hash,
那我们的做法是...
we're going to have a hash table,
建立一张哈希表
we're going to hash into slots,
但不使用链接技术
but rather than using chaining,
只是哈希到槽里
we're going to have another hash table there.
然后我们再建立另一张哈希表
We're going to do a second hash into the second hash table.
在第二个表里做二次哈希
And the idea is that we're going to do it in such a way
通过这种方法 我们就能实现
that we have no collisions at level two.
在第二级没有碰撞
So we may have collisions at level one.
虽然在第一级可能会发生碰撞
We'll take anything that collides at level one
但我们要把碰撞限制在第一级
and put them into a hash table
先把键放入一级哈希表
and then our second level hash table,
然后是再放进二级哈希表
but that hash table, no collisions.
但在二级哈希表里  没有碰撞
Boom. We're just going to hash right in there.
完美匹配 恰好都能哈希到这里面
And it'll just go boom to its thing.
刚刚好平均到每个槽
So let's draw a picture of this to illustrate the scheme.
画一个图来说明这个结构
OK, so we have -- -- 0 one, let's say six, m minus one.
这里有0，1...6...到m-1
So here's our hash table.
这是我们的哈希表
And what we're going to do is
我们要做的是
we're going to use universal hashing at the first level, OK.
在第一级使用全域哈希
So we find a universal hash function.
找一个全域哈希函数
We pick a hash function at random.
随机选择一个哈希函数
And what we'll do is we'll hash into that level.
把键哈希映射到这一级上
And then what we'll do is we'll keep track of two things.
然后我们要注意两件事
One is what the size of the hash table is at the next level.
一件是 下一级的哈希表有多大
So in this case, the size of the hash table
在这里 哈希表的大小
will only use the number of slots.
就用槽数来表示
There's going to be four.  And we're also going to
这里是4  另外 我们还要
keep a separate hash key for the second level.
为第二级保留一个独立的哈希键
So each slot will have its own hash function
这样 每个槽里都定义了一个哈希函数
for the second level.
给下一级哈希用
So for example, this one might
比如 这个可能有
have a key of 31 that is a random number.
一个键值为31的随机数
The a's here. a's up there.
a在这里...在上面
There we go, a's up there.
a在那里
So that's going to be the basis of my hash function,
而这个数就和将要被哈希的键一起
the key with which I'm going to hash.
组成了哈希函数的基础
This one say has 86. And let's say that this,
这里假设是86
and then we have a pointer to the hash table.
然后 有一个二级哈希表的指针
This is say S_1. And it's got four slots
这个表称为S_1  有四个槽
and we stored up 14 and 27.
里面放着14和27
And these two slots are empty.
另外两个槽为空
And this one for example, had what?
还有这里 举个例子
Two nines.
存了29
So the idea here is that in this case
那在这里 我们的做法是
if we look over all our top level hash function,
当我们先看第一级的全部哈希函数
which I'll just call H,
我们把它们称为H
has that H of 14 is equal to H of 27 is equal to one.
我们有H(14)=H(27)=1
Because we're in slot one.
因为这是槽1
OK, so these two both hash to the same slot
这两个数都哈希到
in the level one hash table.
第一级哈希表里同个槽
This is level one.
这是第一级
And this is level two over here.
这是第二级
So level one hashing, 14 and 27 collided.
在第一级 哈希运算后 14和27碰撞
They went into the same slot here.
它们跑到同一个槽里了
But at level two, they got hashed to different places
但在第二级 它们则被哈希到不同的地方
and the hash function I use is going to be indexed
而我所用的哈希函数
by whatever the random numbers are that
则是被我们选的这个随机数...
I chose and found for those
所标记
and I'll show you how we find those.
我会说明如何选择这个随机数
We have then h of 31 of 14 is equal to
h_31(14)=1
one h of 31 of 27 is equal to two.
h_31(27)=2
For level two.
这是第二级的哈希
So I go, hash in here, find the,
在第一级  我们哈希到这
use this as the basis of my hash function
把它作为二级哈希的基底
to hash into whatever table I've got here.
然后再哈希到这边的表里
And so, if there are no,
如果没有...
if I can guarantee that there are no collisions at level two,
如果能保证在第二级没有碰撞
this is going to cost me Order one time
那我只需要花费O(1)的时间
in the worst case to look something up.
就能在最坏情况下 完成数据的查找
How do I look it up? Take the value.
如何查找？用这个值
I apply h to it. That takes me to some slot.
代入函数h 哈希到某个槽
Then I look to see what the key is for this hash function.
再看一下 二级哈希函数的键是多少
I apply that hash function
再用这个哈希函数
and that takes me to another slot.
哈希到另外一个槽
Then I go there.
这样就完成了
And that took me basically two applications
整个过程应用了两个哈希函数
of hash functions plus some look-up,
外加一些查找操作
plus who knows what minor amount of bookkeeping.
还有一些小的 类似记录的操作
So the reason we're going to
那么  为什么在这一级...
have no collisions at this level is the following.
不会发生碰撞的原因如下:
If they're n sub i items that hash to a level one slot i,
如果有n_i个项  被同时哈希到第一级表的槽i
then we're going to use m sub i,
那我们则有m_i个槽——
which is equal to n sub i squared slots
m_i=n_i^2
in the level two hash table.
——m_i个槽在第二级哈希表里
OK, so I should have mentioned here
我应该在这里提过
this is going to be m sub i,
这里是m_i
the size of the hash table
哈希表的大小
and this is going to be my a sub i essentially.
这里是a_i
So I'm going to use,  so basically I'm going to
实际上 我们是把n_i个项
hash n sub i things into n sub i squared locations here.
分别哈希到n_i^2个位置里
So this is going to be incredibly sparse.
因此 第二级表将会非常稀疏
OK, it's going to be quadratic in size.
它的大小是一级表的二次方
And so what I'm going to show is that under those circumstances,
那我要证明的是  在这种情况下
it's easy for me to find hash functions
我们很容易就能找到
such that there are no collisions.
不会发生碰撞的哈希函数
That's the name of the game.
这就是为什么叫完全哈希
Figure out how can I make these hash functions
试想一下 我要怎样才能让这些哈希函数
so that there are no collisions.
不发生碰撞
So that's why I draw this with so few elements here.
这就是为什么我在这里只写了很少的元素
So here for example, I have two elements
举个例子 我有两个元素
and I have a hash table size four here.
那我的表的大小就是4
I have three elements.
三个元素的话
I need a hash table size nine.
表的大小就是9
OK, if there are a hundred elements,
如果有100个元素
I need a hash table size 10,000.
表的大小就是10,000
I'm not going to pick something
大小不是我定的
so there's likely that there's anything of that size.
这个大小可能是任意的东西
And then the fact that this actually works
实际上  这种算法是可行的
and gives us all the properties that we want,
它还具备了我们想要的所有性质
that's part of the analysis. So does everybody see that
这是分析的一部分 大家都懂了吧？
this takes Order one worst case time
它在最坏情况下时间为O(1)
and what the basic structure of it is?
还有它的基础结构是什么？
These things, by the way,
顺便说一下 这里所用的哈希键
are not in this case prime.
不一定是用质数
I could always pick primes that were close to this.
虽然我可以像这样找一些质数
I didn't do that in this case.
但我在这里并没有这样做
Or I could use a universal hash function that
又或者 我可以用一个全域哈希函数
in fact would work for things other than primes.
实际效果要比用质数更好
But I didn't do that for this example.
但在这个例子里 我也没有使用
We all ready for analysis?
都准备好了没？ 要进行分析了
OK, let's do some analysis then.
好的 我们开始做些分析
And this is really pretty analysis.
这确实是一个美妙的分析
Partly as you'll see because we've
你们可能也有这种感觉
already done some of this analysis.
因为我们已经做了一部分分析了
So the trick is analyzing level two.
技巧在于 对第二级的分析
That's the main thing that I want to analyze,
这是我要分析的主要内容
to show that I can find hash functions here that are going to,
我们要证明  我们能找到一种哈希函数
when I map them into, very sparsely,
使得数据到数组的映射
into these arrays here, that in fact,
变得非常的稀疏  而实际上
such hash functions exist
这样的哈希函数是存在的
and I can compute them in advance.
而且我可以事先把它们算出来
So that I have a good way of storing those.
所以我们能把它们很好地存起来
So here's the theorem we're going to use.
那么 这就是我们即将用到的定理
My hash n keys into m equals n squared slots
如果我们把n个键哈希映射到m=n^2个槽里
using a random hash function in a universal set H.
而用到的哈希函数  是从全域集合H里随机挑选的话
Then the expected number of collisions is less than one half.
那么期望的碰撞次数 则小于1/2
OK. The expected number of collisions
碰撞次数的期望值
I don't expect there to be even one collision.
我不希望它发生哪怕一次碰撞
I expect there to be less than half a collision on average.
我希望平均下来 只发生小于半次的碰撞
And so, let's prove this,
好的 我们来证明它
so that the probability that two given keys
那么  对于两个给定的键
collide under h is what?
碰撞的几率是多少？
What's the probability that two given keys collide under h
对于两个给定的键  经过h哈希后  碰撞的概率是多少？
when h is chosen randomly from the universal set?
如果h是从全域集合里随机挑选出来的话？
One over m. Right? That's the definition, right,
1/m  对 这是定义
of, which is in this case equal to one over n squared.
那在这个情况下 它就等于1/（n^2）
So now how many keys,
那现在有多少个...
how many pairs of keys do I have in this table?
在这个表里有多少对键...
How many keys could possibly collide with each other?
有多少对键可能会发生碰撞？
OK. So that's basically just looking at how many different pairs of keys
这其实是要通过键对的数量
do I have to evaluate this for.
来评估这条式子
So that's n choose two pairs of keys.
有（n 2）对键
n choose two pairs of keys.
（n 2）对键
So therefore, the expected number of collisions is
因此 碰撞次数的期望值等于
while for each of these n, not n over two.
对于这里...错了 不是n/2
n choose two pairs of keys.
对于这（n 2)对键的每一对
The probability that it collides is one in n squared.
发生碰撞的概率都是1/n^2
So that's equal to n times n minus one over two,
所以这里等于n(n-1)/2
if you remember your formula, times one in n squared.
如果你还记得公式  然后再乘以1/n^2
And that's less than a half.
这个值小于1/2
So for every pair of keys,
对于每对键都成立
so those of you who remember from 6.042 the birthday paradox,
哪些同学还记得6.042课程里说的生日悖论
this is related to the birthday paradox a little bit.
这和生日悖论有一点点相关
But here I basically have a large set,
但这是一个大的集合
and I'm looking at all pairs,
而且我要照顾到所有的键对
but my set is sufficiently big that the odds
但哈希表是足够大的  以致于
that I get a collision is relatively small.
发生碰撞的概率相对很小
If I start increasing it beyond the square root of m,
但如果我把元素的数量增大
OK, the number of elements,
并且超过根号m
it starts getting bigger in the square root of m
如果元素数量超过了根号m
then the odds of a collision go up dramatically
那么碰撞几率会急剧上升
as you know from the birthday paradox.
正如你们学过的生日悖论
But if I'm less than, if I'm really sparse in there,
但如果n小于根号m  如果空间非常稀疏
I don't get collisions.
就不会碰撞
Or at least I get a relatively small number expected.
或至少得出一个相对较小的期望值
Now I want to remind you of something
那现在 我想让你们回忆起某些内容
which actually in the past I have just assumed,
实际上刚才已经用到过
but I want to actually go through it briefly.
但我想简单地分析一下
It's Markov's inequality.
就是马尔可夫不等式
So who remembers Markov's inequality?
谁还记得马尔可夫不等式？
Don't everybody raise their hand at once.
还记得贝尔加湖畔的马尔科夫吗？
So Markov's inequality says the following.
马尔可夫不等式说的是...
This is one of these great probability facts.
它是最伟大的概率定理之一
For random variable x which is bounded below by 0,
对于下界为0的随机变量x
says the probability that x is bigger than,
x大于或等于...
greater than or equal to any given value T
任意给定的t的概率
is less than or equal to the expectation of x divided by T.
不超过x的期望值除以t
It's a great fact.
一个伟大的定理
Doesn't happen if x isn't bound below by 0.
虽然x的下界不为0 则不成立
But it's a great fact.
但仍然是个伟大的定理
It allows me to relate the probability
它把概率和期望...
of an event to its expectation.
关联在一起
And the idea is in general that
我们通常理解为
if the expectation is going to be small,
如果期望值很小
then I can't have a high probability
那出现大的随机变量值
that the value of the random variable is large.
的概率也很小
It doesn't make sense.
因为那讲不通
How could you have a high probability that it's a million
因为你不可能满足 一百万的概率很高
when my expectation is one or in this case
而同时你的期望只有1  而在这里
we're going to apply it when the expectation is a half?
我们的期望更是只有1/2
Couldn't happen.
那是不可能的
And the proof follows just directly
而它的证明则是恰恰
on the definition of expectation,
直接用到了期望的定义
and so I'm doing this for a discrete random variable.
所以我这里就要用到离散的随机变量
So the expectation by definition is
那么 期望值的定义是
just the sum from little x goes to 0 to infinity of x
∑（x=0到∞）
times the probability that
小写x乘以
my random variable takes on the value x.
Pr(X=x)
That's the definition.
这就是定义
And now it's just a question of doing
现在接下来 我们要做的
like the coarsest approximation you can imagine.
就是你能想像到的最粗糙的近似
First of all, let me just simply throw away all small terms
首先 直接去除所有小的项
that can be greater to or equal to x equals T to infinity of x
它大于或等于 ∑（x=t到∞）
times the probability that x is equal to little x.
小写x乘以Pr(X=x)
So just throw away all the low order terms.
这样就去掉了所有低顺次的数
Now what I'm going to do is replace every one of these terms
接下来 我们要把这些每一项里的小写x
is lower bounded by the value x equals T.
都替换成下界x=t
So that's just the summation of x equals T to infinity of T
这里变成 ∑（x=t到∞）
times the probability that x equals x.
t乘以Pr(X=x)
OK. Over x going from T larger.
从x大于t开始
Because these are only bigger values.
因为这些值只可能更大
And that's just equal then to T,
那这式子就等于t...
because I can pull that out,
因为能把t写在外面
and the summation of x equals T to infinity of the probability
并且x从t到正无穷的
that x equals x is just the probability
X=x概率的总和
that x is greater than or equal to T.
也就是x大于或等于t的概率
And that's done because I just divide by T.
完成证明  因为只要把t除过去
So that's Markov's inequality.
就得到马尔可夫不等式
Really dumb. Really simple.
非常整洁 非常简单
There are much stronger things like Chebyshev bounds
比诸如切比雪夫不等式
and Chernoff bounds and things of that nature.
切尔诺夫不等式之类的更加强大
But Markov's is like unbelievably simple and useful.
但是马尔可夫不等式 却出乎意料地简单而实用
So we're going to just apply that as a corollary.
所以我们打算把它做为一个引理来运用一下
So the probability now of no collisions,
那么 没有碰撞的概率
when I hash n keys into n squared slots
当我们用一个全域哈希函数
using a universal hash function,
把n个键哈希到n^2个槽时
I claim is the probability of no collisions
我称之为没有碰撞的概率
is greater than or equal to a half.
它大于或等于1/2
So I pick a hash function at random.
那我随机选择一个哈希函数
What are the odds that I got no collisions
把这n个键哈希到n^2个槽时
when I hashed those n keys into n squared slots?
没有碰撞的概率是多少
Answer. Probability is I have no collisions is at least a half.
答案是 无碰撞的几率至少也有1/2
Half the time I'm guaranteed that there won't be a collision.
我保证至少一半的情况不会有碰撞
And the proof, pretty simple.
证明相当简单
The probability of no collisions is
无碰撞的概率
the same as the probability as,
与之相同的概率
sorry, is one minus the probability
抱歉 是1减去
that I have at most one collision.
至多一个碰撞的概率
So the odds that I have at least one collision,
抱歉 是至少一个碰撞的概率
the odds that I have at least one collision,
至少有一个碰撞的概率
probability greater than or equal to one collision
发生大于或等于1次碰撞的概率
is less than or equal to,
小于或等于...
now I just apply Markov's inequality with this.
运用马尔可夫不等式
So it's just the expected number of collisions
等于碰撞的期望值
---- divided by one.
——除以1
And that is by Markov's inequality less than,
由马尔可夫不等式可知  小于...
by definition, excuse me, of expected number of collisions,
由定义 不好意思 碰撞的期望值
which we've already shown, is less than a half.
已经证明过了 小于1/2
So the probability of at least one collision is less than a half.
所以至少一次碰撞的概率小于1/2
The probability of 0 collisions is at least a half.
那么 0碰撞的概率 就至少是1/2
So we're done here.
毕明完毕
So to find a good level to hash function is easy.
所以  要找一个好的哈希函数是很容易的
I just test a few at random.
随机测试几个
Most of them out there,
它们的大部分
OK, half of them, at least half of them are going to work.
至少一半都是可行的
So this is in some sense, if you think about it,
这在某种程度上 你可以想一下
a randomized construction,
它就是一个随机化的架构
because I can't tell you which one it's going to be.
因为我说不准哪个是可行的
It's non-constructive in that sense,
虽然这样说 它好像是无结构的
but it's a randomized construction.
但它是一个随机化结构
But they have to exist because most of them
所以必定会存在有效函数  因为它们大部分
out there have this good property.
都有好的性质
So I'm going to be able to find for each one of these,
所以我能够从他们之中找到...
I just test a few at random, and I find one.
只要随机测试几个 就能找到一个
Test a few at random, find one, etc.
再测试几个 就又有一个
Fill in my table there.
然后写进表里
Because all that is pre-computation.
因为所有的函数都是预先计算好的
And I'm going to find them
那我就想要把它们找出来
because the odds are good that one exists.
因为有效的函数存在的概率是很大的
So -- --
所以——
we just test a few at random.
只需要随机测试几个
And we'll find one quickly ----
就能很快地找到一个
since at least half will work.
因为至少一半是有效可行的
I just want to show that there exists good ones.
我只需要证明存在有效的函数
All I have to prove is that
其实我只要证明
at least one works for each of these cases.
对于每种情况至少都有一个是可行的
In fact, I've shown that there's a huge number that will work.
实际上 我们已经证明绝大多数都是可行的
Half of them will work.
起码有一半是可行的
But to show it exists, I would just have to show that
但如果只是证明它是存在的 那我就只需要证明
the probability was greater than 0.
其概率大于0
So to finish up, we need to still analyze the storage
为了完善 我们还需要分析一下存储
because I promised in my theorem that
因为我保证过在这个定理中
the table would be of size order n.
表的大小仅为O(n)
And yet now I've said
但我也说过
there's all of these quadratic-sized slots here.
这里所有的槽数都是二次方阶的大小
So I'm going to show that that's order n.
所以我要证明 这是O(n)大小
So for level one, that's easy.
对于第一级 很简单
We'll just choose the number of slots
我会把槽的数量
to be equal to the number of keys.
设成等于键的数量
And that way the storage at level one is just order n.
这样第一级的存储就是O(n)
And now let's let n sub i
然后 我们令n_i
be the random variable for the number of keys
做为被哈希到表T的槽i里 所有键的数量
——that hash to slot i in T.
——的一个随机变量
OK, so n sub i is just what we've called it.
n_i就是之前提到的
Number of elements that slot there.
槽i所拥有的键数
And we're going to use m sub i equals n sub i squared slots
对于每个二级表S_i
in each level two table S sub i.
我们都设槽数m_i=n_i^2
So the expected total storage
那么  总存储空间的期望值等于
——is just n for level one, order n if you want,
——第一级的n 也可以说是O(n)
but basically n slots for level one plus the expected value,
因为第一级是n个槽  然后再加上
whatever I expect the sum of i equals 0 to m minus one
∑（i=0到m-1）Θ(n_i^2)
of theta of n sub i squared to be.
的期望值
Because I basically have to add up the square
因为我要把所有二级表的...
for every element that applies here,
平方阶大小全部加起来
the square of what's in there.
每一个二级表的平方阶大小
Who recognizes this summation?
谁认得这个总和？
Where have we seen that before?
在哪里见过？
Who attends recitation?
谁去了复习课？
Where have we seen this before? What's the --
我们在复习课上见过这式子？
We're summing the expected value of a bunch of
这里是加上一个一大块东西的期望...
——Yeah, what was that algorithm?
对 是什么算法？
We did the sorting algorithm, right?
是个排序算法 是吧？
What was the sorting algorithm for which
在什么排序算法里
this was an important thing to evaluate?
它是一个重要的测量值？
Don't everybody shout it out at once.
有谁知道马上大声说出来
What was that sorting algorithm called?
那个排序算法叫什么？
Bucket sort. Good. Bucket sort.
桶排序 对了 就是桶排序
Yeah. We showed that the sum of the squares of random variables
当变量随机分布到n个桶时
when they're falling randomly into n bins is order n. Right?
我们证明过它们平方的总和 是Θ(n)  对吧？
And you can also out of this get a,
你也可以从这里得出一个...
as we did before, get a probability bound.
正如之前所做的 得出一个概率界限
What's the probability that it's more than
根据这个期望  可以用马尔科夫不等式
a certain amount times n using Markov's inequality.
得到总储存空间大于n乘以某个值的概率
But this is the key thing is we've seen this analysis.
这是分析的关键点
OK, we used it there in time, so there's a little bit,
恰好这里用得上 有点巧合
but that's one of the reasons we study
但这也是我们在学期的开始
sorting at the beginning of the term is
就学习排序的原因之一
because the techniques of sorting,
因为排序的技巧
they just propagate into all these other areas of analysis.
会应用到其它的分析领域
You see a lot of the same kinds of things.
你会发现很多相似的情况
And so now that you know bucket sort clearly so well,
因为你们已经清楚地理解了桶排序
now you know that this without having to do any extra work.
所以能很快得出结果 不用做多余的工作
So you might want to go back
但你们回去可能要
and review your bucket sort analysis,
再复习一下桶排序的分析
because it's applied now.
因为在这里会用到
Same analysis. Two places.
一样的分析 用在两个地方
OK. Good recitation this Friday,
做好复习 在本周五
which will be a quiz review and we have a quiz next,
我们会有一个复习测验 接下来还有测验
there's no class on Monday,
周一没有课
but we have a quiz on next Wednesday.
下周三做一个测验
OK, so good luck everybody on the quiz.
希望到时大家有不错的表现
Make sure you get plenty of sleep.
确保有足够的睡眠